<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>http://spooner.github.com/</id>
  <title>Spooner's Blog</title>
  <updated>2011-12-02T23:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://spooner.github.com/"/>
  <link rel="self" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/spooner_blog"/>
  <author>
    <name>Spooner (Bil Bas)</name>
    <uri>http://spooner.github.com</uri>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:spooner.github.com,2011-12-02:/blog/2011/12/set-up-new-nanoc-generated-website/</id>
    <title type="html">Set up new nanoc-generated website</title>
    <published>2011-12-02T23:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2011-12-02T23:00:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://spooner.github.com/blog/2011/12/set-up-new-nanoc-generated-website/"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href="http://nanoc.stoneship.org/"&gt;nanoc&lt;/a&gt; in order to generate a bit more interesting site. Previously, I just had a single, hand-generated page, which was fine as a list of links really, but it wasn’t useful as a showcase of my projects and I quite liked the idea of having my own blog. Whether I’ll blog more than once a year or not, is another question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://nanoc.stoneship.org/"&gt;nanoc&lt;/a&gt; seems to be pretty good overall and I think it was a better choice for me than &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, which I’d used previously (this is because &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; can be used to directly host at &lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, which is good, but it doesn’t support HAML in that usage, which is bad). It isn’t too complicated to set up and I use HAML for layout, kramdown for content and Sass for style quite nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that dismays me a little with &lt;a href="http://nanoc.stoneship.org/"&gt;nanoc&lt;/a&gt; is that you have to manually manage rules for compilation and routing, when it could have much more reasonable defaults set up and a bit more assumption of standard practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it is probably not exemplary, but the generator source for this whole site is freely available at &lt;a href="https://github.com/Spooner/spooner.github.com/tree/generator"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href="http://nanoc.stoneship.org/"&gt;nanoc&lt;/a&gt; in order to generate a bit more interesting site. Previously, I just had a single, hand-generated page, which was fine as a list of links really, but it wasnÔÇÖt useful as a showcase of my projects and I quite liked the idea of having my own blog. Whether IÔÇÖll blog more than once a year or not, is another question.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
